

# Alejandro O. Valdés DATA SCIENTIST

#### **PROFESSIONAL SKILLS**

- -SQL (MySQL, PostgreSQL)
- -Python (NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn,

Keras)

- -Django
- -Latex
- -MATLAB
- -Git
- D
- -AWS Athena(SQL)
- -Java
- -Power BI
- -Tableau
- -C, C++ and C#.

## **PERSONAL SKILLS**

- -Ability to analyze complex technical information
- -Reliable and professional
- -Detail orientation
- -Time management
- -Team player
- -Fast learner
- -Motivated

### **LANGUAGES**

- Native: Spanish
- Fluent: English

#### **CONTACT**

631327628

aovaldes@gmail.com

https://github.com/aovaldes2

https://aovaldes2.github.io/Alejandro-O-Valdes-Portfolio

Leganés, Madrid

# **ABOUT ME**

Data Scientist graduated in mathematics with multiple postgraduate studies and experience in education and as a data analyst. With a teamoriented attitude, I am always eager to contribute with my abilities in programming and applied mathematics.

## **EXPERIENCE**

# Grantia Capital, SGIIC,SA

Feb 2023 - Present

#### **Python Developer**

Development of programs for task automation in Back Office and Trading departments. Evaluation and proposal of improvements to existing strategies. Statistical and quantitative analysis of new investment strategies.

#### Freelance

Nov 2021 - Dic 2022

#### **Data Scientist**

- Analysis of key metrics for the Human Resources department. Development of intuitive Power BI dashboards to evaluate performance and efficiency in human resources management.
- Development of an ensemble model (XGBoost, Catboost, and Random Forest) algorithm to predict the probability of employee retention.

#### Private teacher (MATH, PROGRAMMING)

Provided personalized tutoring services in Mathematics and Programming to help students improve their understanding and performance in these subjects.

#### Openbank

Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

#### **Data Analyst (traineeship)**

- -Migration project:
- Analysis of controls generated for migration.
- Resolution of incidents obtained in the data cleansing process.
- Creation of Excel reports, dashboards and performing data validation activities.
- -Business Analytics for T&O:
- Implemented ETL processes from various sources to QuickSight using AWS Athena (SQL).
- Created different types of dashboards in Amazon QuickSight, including static, interactive, analytical, and temporal.

# **University of Havana**

Sep 2016 - Feb 2017

#### Math teacher

Teaching Mathematics I in the degree of Food Sciences.

# **Technological University of Havana**

Aug 2014 - Aug 2016

#### Math teacher

Teaching multiple engineering courses, including Mathematics I, II, and IV and Numerical Mathematics.

# **EDUCATION**

#### The Bridge Digital Talent Accelerator

2021

• Bootcamp Data Science

#### **University Carlos III of Madrid**

2018 - 2020

• Master of Science, Mathematical Engineering

#### **University of Havana**

2010 - 2014

• Bachelor of Science, Mathematics



# Alejandro O. Valdés DATA SCIENTIST

# **APTITUDES TÉCNICAS**

- -SQL (MySQL, PostgreSQL)
- -Python (NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn,

Keras)

- -Django
- -Latex
- -MATLAB
- -Git
- D
- -AWS Athena(SQL)
- -lava
- -Power BI
- -Tableau
- -C, C++ and C#.

#### **APTITUDES PERSONALES**

- -Capacidad para analizar información técnica compleja
- -Confiable y profesional
- -Orientación al detalle
- -Gestión del tiempo
- -Trabajo en equipo
- -Facilidad para el aprendizaje

# **IDIOMAS**

- Nativo: Spanish
- Fluido: English

### **CONTACTO**

631327628

aovaldes@gmail.com

https://github.com/aovaldes2

https://aovaldes2.github.io/Alejandro-O-Valdes-Portfolio

Leganés, Madrid

# **PERFIL**

Data Scientist graduado en matemáticas con múltiples estudios de postgrado y experiencia en el sector educativo y como analista de datos. Orientado al trabajo en equipo y siempre estoy dispuesto a contribuir con mis habilidades en la programación y las matemáticas aplicadas.

# **EXPERIENCIA LABORAL**

# Grantia Capital, SGIIC,SA

Feb 2023 - Present

#### **Python Developer**

Desarrollo para la automatización de tareas en los departamentos de Back Office y de Trading. Evaluación y propuestas de mejora de las estrategias ya existentes.. Análisis estadístico y cuantitativo de nuevas estrategias de inversión.

#### **Freelance**

Nov 2021 - Dic 2022

#### **Data Scientist**

- Análisis de métricas relevantes para el departamento de Recursos Humanos.
   Desarrollo de dashboards intuitivos en Power BI para evaluar el rendimiento y la eficiencia del personal.
- Desarrollo de un modelo ensemble (XGBoost, Catboost y Random Forest)para predecir la probabilidad de retención de empleados en la empresa.

#### Private teacher (MATH, PROGRAMMING)

Brindar servicios personalizados de tutoría en Matemáticas y Programación para ayudar a los estudiantes a mejorar su comprensión y desempeño.

#### **Openbank**

Mar 2020 - Aug 2020

#### **Data Analyst (traineeship)**

- -Proyecto de migración:
- Análisis de controles generados para la migración.
- Resolución de incidencias obtenidas en el proceso de limpieza.
- Informes en Excel, dashboards y realizar actividades de validación de datos.
- -Business Analytics para T&O:
- Implementar procesos ETL desde varias fuentes a QuickSight utilizando AWS Athena (SQL).
- Crear diferentes tipos de dasboards en Amazon QuickSight, incluyendo estáticos, interactivos, analíticos y temporales.

# **University of Havana**

Sep 2016 - Feb 2017

## Math teacher

Enseñar Matemática I en el grado de Ciencias de la Alimentación.

# Universidad Tecnológica de la Habana

Aug 2014 - Aug 2016

#### Math teacher

Enseñar en múltiples cursos de ingeniería, incluidos Matemáticas I, II, and IV y Matemática Numérica.

# HISTORIAL ACADÉMICO

## **The Bridge Digital Talent Accelerator**

2021

• Bootcamp Data Science

#### **Universidad Carlos III de Madrid**

2018 - 2020

• Master en Ingieneria Matemática

#### Universidad de la Habana

2010 - 2014

• Licenciatura en Matemáticas